Guide to the Djibril Tamsir Niane Audiorecordings Documenting Guinean Oral Traditions
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- "L'histoire Mamoudou 4 Maninka", Circa 1965-1975; Tape 36; 1 (Box 36)
  Track A: The Story of Facily Keita and Other Tales of Maninka Life. Narrative and vocals, guitar music, includes a lament on the death of Sunjata and a claim that he was buried in a cave at Nora.
  Track A: Récit et chant, musique a la guitare, incluant une lamentation de la mort de Sunjata et prétendant qu'il est enterré dans une grotte à Nora.
- "Mamaya Kankan", Circa 1970-1979; Tape 37; 1 (Box 37)
  Track A: Léopold Sédar Senghor, President of Senegal. A French radio interview broadcast in Dakar, Senegal on the topic of négritude.
  Track A: Émission en français de la radio de Dakar, Sénégal sur la question de la négritude.
- "Musique", Circa 1960-1979; Tape 38; 1 (Box 38)
  Track A: Guinean Fusion Music and Mande Oral Tradition. Maninka orchestra to 11:00; Bamana language male vocalist with guitar introducing a band, and singing about the Bamana Segou hero Bakari Jan.
  Track B: Guinean Big Band Music on the Radio. Radio broadcast from Conakry, including the song "Tinkisso".
  Track C: Guinean Big Band Music on the Radio. Radio broadcast from Conakry, Guinea.
  Track D: Guinean Big Band Music on the Radio. Radio broadcast from Conakry, Guinea.
  Track A: Orchestre Malinké en 11:00; une voix masculine en langue Bambara avec une guitare introduisant une bande et des chants concernant des Bambara de Ségou et le héros Bakari Jan.
  Track B: Émission radio à Conakry incluant la chanson "Tinkisso".
  Track C: Émission radio à Conakry, Guinée.
  Track D: Émission radio à Conakry, Guinée.
- "L'histoire Yanké Waly 15", Circa 1970-1979; Tape 39; 1 (Box 39)
  Track A: Part 3, Sunjata fasa (an episode of the Sunjata epic) by Mori Kanté. Live concert in honor of Djibril Tamsir Niane, continued from Tape 27, Track A and Tape 32, Track A.
  Track A: Concert live en honneur de Djibril Tamsir Niane, la suite de Tape 27, Track A et Tape 32, Track A.
- "Nouveautés du Disque 14", Circa 1970-1979; Tape 40; 1 (Box 40)
  Track A: Muslim Prayer Sessions of Guinea and Senegal. Futa and Toucouleur dialects of the Pular language including a Wolof-speaker asking for blessings and a sermon praising President Senghor of Senegal.
  Track A: Dialectes du Fouta et des Toucouleurs dans langue poular incluant quelqu'un parlant le wolof et qui demande des bénédictions et un sermon de louange au président Senghor du Sénégal.
- "Conference de M=2 N 16", Circa 1965-1975; Tape 41; 1 (Box 41)
  Track A: Traditional West African Music. Female Maninka chorus with ngoni music; guitar instrumental with Bamana vocals.
  Track A: Choriste malinké avec la musique ngoni; musique à la guitare avec une voix bambara.
- Djibril Tamsir Niane Radio Interview, Circa 1970-1975; Tape 42; 1 (Box 42)
  Track A: Djibril Tamsir Niane interview at Africa Center in London, Niane replies to questions about oral tradition and the Fondation L.S. Senghor in Dakar.
  Track A: Entretien en français au centre africain à Londres, les réponses de Niane concernant la tradition orale et la Fondation L.S. Senghor à Dakar.
- "Musique Bonne", Circa 1965-1970; Tape 43; 1 (Box 43)
  Track A: A Radio Broadcast of Maninka Music. A Guinean orchestra with a male vocalist.
  Track A. Un orchestre guinéen avec une voix masculine.
- "Les Enfants", Circa 1970-1975; Tape 44; 1 (Box 44)
  Track A. West African School Children. A child speaking Fulfulde and reciting a story about an orphan named Sulayman and his dog; changes to Susu language singing; other children recite poetry and sing songs in French.
  Track B. Radio Broadcast of Orchestra Music. Begins with Cuban orchestra followed by French chanteuse, then back to Cuban music.
  Track C: Radio Broadcast. Cuban band music.
  Track A. Un enfant parlant le peul et récitant une histoire concernant un orphelin appelé Sulayman et son chien, change en chantant dans la langue susu; d'autres enfants récitent des poésies, de chants et des chanson en français.
  Track B: Un orcheste cubain commence, accompagné par une chanteuse française, puis revient à la musique cubaine.
  Track C: Musique cubaine.
- "Concert de l'ensemble instrumental de la Radio et concert de Kankan Boloba ", Circa 1960-1975; Tape 45; 1 (Box 45)
  Track A. A Guinean Fusian Orchestra and Traditional Oral Epic. Music at Club Fiyé Jazz, Orchestre de Finyéran led by Musa Diakité tenor sax, Lancei Kouyaté guitar, Buréma Sakho toumbi, Oumar Doumbouya bolon (warriors' calabash harp) playing "Kulanjan" and "Soboku"; unknown venue, Seck Mamadou Fall Doumbouya (born 1924) village of Waran, Siguiri region, recites from the Sunjata epic.
  Track B. An Episode of the Sunjata Epic. The buffalo woman and the Traoré brothers aquiring Sogolon for Sunjata's father, narrated in Maninka by Sekou Amadu Fall Doumbouya who was not a jeli.
  Track C: Two Sycophantic Songs for the PDG (Partie Démocratique Guinéen). 1. Susu language, little girls chanting "My Mother Touré"; 2. Baga Foré language, little girls chanting "PDG"
  Track A. Musique au Club Fiyé Jazz, Orchestre de Finyéran dirigé par Musa Diakité au saxophone, Lancei Kouyaté à la guitare, Buréma Sakho au toumbi, Oumar Doumbouya au bolon (harpe de calebasse des guerriers) jouant "Kulanjan" et "Soboku"; endroit inconnu, Seck Mamadou Fall Doumbouya (né en 1924) village de Waran, région de Siguiri, raconte une partie de l'épopée de Soundjata.
  Track B: La femelle buffle et les frères Traoré ont acquis Sogolon pour le père de Soundiata, raconter en malinké par Sekou Amadu Fall Doumbouya qui n'etait pas un jeli.
  Track C: 1. En langue susu, les petites filles chantent "Ma Mère Touré"; 2. En langue Baga Foré, les petites filles chantent "PDG".
- "Koce Barema" and "12/2/74, 2-3-4", Circa 1968-1969; Tape 46; 1 (Box 46)
  Track A: [blank track]
  Track B. "The Mansa's Four Tufts of Hair" and other Stories. Djibril Tamsir Niane leading a Guinean cultural group collecting oral tradition, interviews a woman in Dinguiraye who told stories in the Maninka and Fulfulde languages.
  Track C: Two National Anthems. First three minutes blank, then approximately three minutes of American blues-jazz, long blank space, ends with the Star Spangled Banner and the national anthem of the Republic of Mali.
  Track B: Djibril Tamsir Niane dirigeant un groupe culturel guinéen pour la collecte des traditions orales, entretien avec une femme de Dinguiraye qui raconte des histoires en malinké et en peul.
  Track C: Les trois premières minutes sont vides, ensuite environ trois minutes de blues et de jazz américain, un long espace vide, terminé par la Star Spangled Banner et l'hymne national de la République du Mali.
- "Niani Kadia Kama", 1968; Tape 47; 1 (Box 47)
  Track A. Maninka Women's Music at Niani, Guinea continued from Tape 23, Track A. First five minutes, jelimusolu singing and clapping to jenbé music, followed by continuation of Djibril Tamsir Niane's interview with Jelimuso Tata, ends after seven minutes, with jenbé music to the end of the tape.
  Track A. Les cinq premières minutes, une jelimusolu chante au son des batements du la musique jenbe, suivie par la suite de l'entretien de Djibril Tamsir Niane avec Jelimuso Tata, après termine par sept minutes de musique jenbe.
- Maninka Jelimuso (female bard) Music, Circa 1965-1975; Tape 48; 1 (Box 48)
  Track A. Singing, drumming, clapping, shouting, punctuated by blasts on a referee's whistle.
  Track B. Sports News from Radio Gambia. Sports news including part of a boxing match broadcast from Banjul.
  Track A: Chant, danse, applaudissements, cries, ponctués par une explosion se referant a des siflets.
  Track B: Des informations sportives incluant une partie d'une émission de match de boxe à Banjul.
- Big Band Music from Radio Senegal, Circa 1970-1979; Tape 49; 1 (Box 49)
  Track A. First 18 minutes, a Senegalese orchestra with a Cuban beat followed by a traditional narrative in the Wolof language with political themes.
  Track A. Les dix-huit premières minutes, orchestre sénégalais avec un rythme cubain, suivi par un récit traditionnel en wolof avec un sujet politique.
- Société Africaine d'Edition du Communication (SAEC), Circa 1965-1975; Tape 50; 1 (Box 50)
  Track A. French language, Radio Guinea broadcast, SAEC speaker describing the many kinds of publications issued by them.
  Track A. En français, une émission de la radio guinéenne, l'informateur décrit la SAEC et ses multiples catégories de publications.
- Miscellaneous Speech and Music, Circa 1965-1970; Tape 51; 1 (Box 51)
  Track A. About one minute of Djibril Tamsir Niane and others thanking a government minister, followed by about three minutes of banjo music, approximately thirty seconds of Maninka orchestra, then cuts to another orchestra with Susu singers, then back to a Maninka orchestra.
  Track A. Environ une minute de Djibril Tamsir Niane et d'autres personnes remerciant un ministre du gouvernement, suivie d'environ trois minutes de musique banjo, environ trente secondes d'orchestre malinké, ensuite intervient un autre orchestre de chanteurs susu, ensuite, retour à un orchestre maninka.
- Fula and Mande Oral Tradition, Circa 1965-1970; Taoe 53; 1 (Box 53)
  Track A. Begins with a rapid Muslim blessing in Fulfulde, a brief reading in Arabic, and a Fulfulde story of how the Fula came to Futa Jalon; thanks to Djibril Tamsir Niane and a cultural delegation from Senegal; at 24 minutes changes to Maninka discussion of the seventeenth to the nineteenth century Empire of Gaabu (see Tape 31, Track A), then Pular-speaker Alpha Ba telling the story of Djanka Wali to 1:30; second part starts with date 27 January 1979, interview with background music and chorus about Kankakan koro, Gaabu, Maninka-Fula war, ends with jeli vocals and ngoni music.
  Track A. Commence avec une bénédiction musulmane rapide en peul, une brève lecture en arabe, et une histoire en peul de l'installation des peuls au Fouta-Djalon, les remerciements à Djibril Tamsir Niane et une délégation culturelle du Sénégal.
- Jelimuso Fanta Demba of Mali, Circa 1970-1979; Tape 54; 1 (Box 54)
  Track A. Fanta Demba Koroba (the "old" singer by that name), famous as female political critic, and counterpart to Bansoumana Sissoko; a second singer is Maminyan Demba, songs include "Saba Miniyamba" and "Tara" (the praise song for Al-Hadj 'Umar); final 13 minutes blank.
  Track A. Fanta Demba Koroba (anciennement connue cantatrice sous ce nom), célèbre critique politique féminine, et concitoyenne de Bansoumana Sissoko; une seconde cantatrice est Maminyan Demba, les chansons ont pour titres "Saba Miniyamba" et "Tara" (la geste de El-Hadj 'Umar); dernières treize minutes vides.
- Mori Kanté Sings about Sunjata, Circa 1968; Tape 55; 1 (Box 55)
  Track A. An incomplete repeat recording of Tape 32, Track A.
  Track A. Enregistrement incomplet de Tape 32, Track A.
- A Radio Broadcast Maninka Theatre Piece, Circa 1970-1979; Tape 56; 1 (Box 56)
  Track A. Introduced in French, Maninka kora and guitar music, jelimuso vocals, radio drama with a poem in French.
  Track A. Introduit en français, en kora malinké et en guitare comme musique de fond, voix des jelimusow, programme radiophonique avec un poème en français.
- History and Culture of Baga Villages: M'bottini & Mintani, Circa 1969-1970; Tape 58; 1 (Box 58)
  Track A. Susu language Interviews on the History and Culture of Baga Villages: M'bottini and Mintani. Woodcarvers and masks including Mössölö Kumbo, early settlers, Wurbendo dialect of the Baga Foré, Andisa the sacred table, and interview topics of the Niane research team.
  Track A. Les sculptures en bois et les masques incluant Mössölô Kumbo, les anciens habitants, le dialecte Wurbendo des Baga Foré, Andisa la table sacrée, et les sujets de recherche de l'équipe de Niane.
- The Story of Djanka Wali, Circa 1965-1975; Tape 59; 1 (Box 59)
  Track A. Fulfulde language narrative to kora music.
  Track A. Conte peul accompagné à la kora.
- Praises for Tènèngbè of a Mamaya Troupe, Circa 1965-1970; Tape 60; 1 (Box 60)
  Track A. A repeat recording of Tape 8.
  Track B. Distorted and indecipherable. Garbled, high-speed repeat of Tape 60, Track A with Cuban music in background.
  Track A. Un double enregistrement de Tape 8.
  Track B: Un enregistrement incompréhensible pour cause de vitesse accélérée de Tape 60, Track A d'une musique de fond cubaine.
- English Language Course, Circa 1970-1979; Tape 61; 1 (Box 61)
  Track A. Fifty-three minutes of a series of English language lessons.
  Track A. 53 minutes d'une serite de coursen angláis.
- Ngoni Music from the Ensemble Instrumental National du Mali, Circa 1965-1975; Tape 62; 1 (Box 62)
  Track A. A jeli (professional bard) of Mali, singing in the Khassonké dialect of Manding, switching to the Maraka (Sonkinké) language, praising a war hero named Diadjiri.
  Track A. Un jeli professionel du Mali, chantant en dialecte khassonké du manding, changeant en Maraka (langue Soninké), chantant les louanges d'un héros de guerre appellé Diadjiri.
- History and Culture of Baga Villages: Kamsar, Circa 1969-1970; Tape 63; 1 (Box 63)
  Track A. Susu language Interviews on the History and Culture of Baga Villages: Kamsar. Thierno Mangoya Sylla sings a Baga song to D'mba, talks about masks, dances, rituals, and the story of competition of two groups over the mask Koni (Baga a-Bemp).
  Track A. Thierno Mangoya Sylla chante une chanson Baga du D'mba, parle des masques, des danses, des rituels, et de l'histoire de la compétition de deux groupes sur le masque Koni (Baga a-Bemp).
- "Boloba", Circa 1970-1979; Tape 64; 1 (Box 64)
  Track A. Radio Music from Dakar, Senegal. Orchestra Jazz, Rock & Roll, Blues, Latin.
  Track B. Radio Music from Dakar, Senegal. A wide range of music including West African orchestra.
  Track C: Radio Music from Dakar, Senegal. Rock & Roll, Blues, Jazz.
  Track D: Radio Music from Dakar, Senegal. A wide range of recorded music.
  Track A. Orchestre de Jazz, Rock & Roll, Blues et de latino.
  Track B: Une longue succession de musique incluant l'orchestre Ouest Africain.
  Track C: Rock & Roll, Blues, Jazz.
  Track D: Une longue succession d'enregistrements musicaux.
- Untitled, Circa 1970-1979; Tape 65; 1 (Box 65)
  Track A. Maninka Radio Drama. A radio play about Samori Touré and a soap opera from Maninka National Radio for twenty-seven minutes; the rest is blank.
  Track B. Radio Drama in French on West African Topics. Conquest of the Western Sudan, building the railroad; switches to Maninka telling the story of the siege of Sikasso, Mali.
  Track C: Bala and Mamaya Music. Vocals by the wife of Mori Jeli Kaba for thirty minutes followed by slowed-down distorted voice and women shouting in the Susu language.
  Track D: Ngoni Music on Maninka Topics. A jeli (professional bard) singing about "Simbon" ("the lion") in praise of President Sekou Touré of Guinea, joined by a jelimuso (female bard); from 13:20 to the end, narration to ngoni music of an episode of Sunjata & Fakoli going to Futa Jalon; oral tradition about Kissidougou, Guinea.
  Track A: Une émission radio sur Samori Touré et le feuilleton de la radio nationale en Malinké en 27 minutes; le reste est vide.
  Track B: Conquête du Soudan, construction du chemin de fer; passe en malinké pour raconter l'histoire du siège de Sikasso au Mali.
  Track C: Chant de la femme de Mori Jeli Kaba en 30 minutes suivi d'une voix basse et discordante et des femmes criant en langue Susu.
  Track D: Un jeli professionel interprète une chanson sur "Simbon" ("le lion") en faisant le louange du président Sékou Touré de la Guinée, rejoint par une jelimuso (griotte) de 13:20 à la fin, raconté histoire, avec l'accompagnement d'une musique de ngoni de l'épisode de Sunjata et Fakoli allant au Fouta-Djalon; tradition orale de Kissidougou en Guinée.